Now in this section, we're going to focus on the data foundations for
generative AI on AWS. So what is a need for data foundation?
So data can be primarily used in two areas. First is the generative AI.
So previously, if you remember, when we were discussing model customization on Amazon bedrock,
we said there are three approaches, model distillation, fine tuning, and continued pre-training.
Then we looked at the architecture and said, okay, this is the base model.
And then we're going to use the training data that we have in the S3 bucket to train this model,
and then we'll have a fine-tuned or customized model. But we did not discuss how we can extract
the data from various data sources, cleanse, transform it, and then use it for model customization.
To reach this stage where we have this training data, that's what we're going to discuss in these
next few lectures. The second scenario is traditional machine learning, where you need
data to train your machine learning models that you might have built for your use case.
Now one of the key AWS services on the data side is Amazon SageMaker AI.
So Amazon SageMaker is a fully managed machine learning service.
It is used by data scientists and developers to build, train, and deploy machine learning models.
Now SageMaker AI is essentially a collection of different services.
So it works mainly in three areas. One is to generate example data, as you can see here.
It can help you fetch the data, clean the data, prepare the data,
and then you can also train a model on the service. You can evaluate the performance of the model
and then finally, it can help you deploy the model to production and monitor it in the production
environment. Now before we look at the capabilities of the SageMaker AI in the area of data,
let's take a quick look at machine learning development life cycle. Now from the data processing
side, the first thing you need to do is collect the data. So you need to identify the data sources,
maybe they are outside the organization as a feed, maybe they are within your organization.
They can be streaming data batch data. We need to get the data from data warehouse or a data lake.
So once you have identified and ingested the data, second thing is the data preprocessing.
So as part of data preprocessing, maybe you need to cleanse the data, remove inconsistencies,
missing values, duplicates, maybe you need to partition the data and split data into maybe train,
validate, and test. So once you are complete with data preprocessing, next is the feature engineering.
So as part of the feature engineering, you select a subset of extracted features. Maybe we don't
need the entire feature set. Maybe you only need to partially use the dataset for your use case
or maybe you need to do some form of data transformation or you need to create some additional features.
Now from the generic perspective, once you have this data, you can go ahead and customize your
foundation model. But from the traditional machine learning perspective, once you have this data,
then you're going to train your model, then also evaluate and tune the model based on the
output it generates. And then finally, you will deploy the model and monitor the model in production.
Now let's see how Amazon SageMaker capabilities map to the machine learning life cycle.
So in the data processing phase, we have SageMaker data wrangler, which focuses on data collection
and data preprocessing. So that's the first service we're going to learn in the next few lectures.
Then we have SageMaker feature store, which focuses on the feature engineering part.
Then we have the SageMaker clarify, which focuses on bias detection,
explainability, and model evaluation. So this is the service we're going to discuss in the
responsible AI section. Then we have the SageMaker model monitor, which focuses on
the models that you already deployed and need to monitor in production.
And then we're going to look at ML governor's capabilities, the SageMaker AI offers.
We're going to look at role manager model cards and model dashboard. Again, we're going to discuss
this, not in this section, but in the responsible AI section. And then finally, we have the SageMaker
jumpstart, and we've already discussed this service in the first section. Okay, I'll see you in the next
lecture. Thank you.